Luc Blassel

PhD Student, interested in Machine learning in Biology

⊠ luc.blassel@gmail.com നി lucblassel.com

Paris, France

I am a PhD student in computational biology at the Institut Pasteur in France. I started with biology studies in AgroParisTech, a Parisian "Grande école" but quickly found my way to machine learning. In order to complete my M.Sc, I entered the Institut Pasteur as an intern, and found the fascinating world of academic research.

I have since continued on, entering a PhD program in computational biology, exploring the interface between biology, computer science and machine learning.

This really interdisciplinary experience drives me to further explore computational methods to resolve problems of a biological nature.

Experience

PhD Student, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France

2020-Present

Using machine learning with sequence data. With the ever growing quantity of high quality sequencing data, we are now able to develop methods to take advantage of this data. My PhD project follows 2 different axes: (1) Using machine learning to discover Drug resistance mutations in HIV (Continuation of the M.Sc project) (2) Search of a function space for sequence transformation functions that improve sequence mapping and alignment. This PhD is supervized by Rayan Chikhi and funded by the PRAIRIE institute. Some additional information can be found on the project page

Research Engineer, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France

2018-2020

Using machine learning and large datasets to explore the drug resistance landscape in HIV. Supervized by Olivier Gascuel. A large dataset of UK HIV sequences associated with patient RT-treatment status was used to train several machine learning algorithms. Examining the important learned features gave us insight in mutations associated to ART failure. This project resulted in a publication. Project page here, and M.Sc thesis (in french).

Data Scientist Intern, Capital Data, Paris, France

Mar-Sept 2017

As a data scientist intern at Capital data I was tasked with developing a software pipeline to validate data prior to database integration, and detect anomalies usign time series. This was implemented in R and Python. I also, developed reporting-oriented data visualizations of KPIs using BIME and Tableau. Finally statistical AB-testing was also done using python.

Teaching and tutoring, self-employed, Paris, France

2015-Present

Since the beginning of my higher education, I have beedn tutoring middle school, high school and university students in scientific subjects, mainly mathematics. The aim is to turn the students into independents people, more confident in their abilities and more knowledgeable in order to excel in their respective studies. Since September 2021, I have been doing oral examination in English for PCSI preparatory class students as the ENCPB in Paris, France.

Education

Masters of Science (M.Sc.), Dep. MIDO, Dauphine université, France

2017-2018

during the IASD program, I followed courses in Deep learning, reinforcement learning, statistical modelling, software engineering and data science. This was a double curriculum with the AgroParisTech IODAA program.

Diplôme d'Ingénieur, AgroParisTech, Paris, France

2014-2018

The first two years of this programm are focused on biology with courses in molecular biology, ecology, health, epidemiology and statistics.

During the final year, I followed the IODAA program, which was done as a double curriculum with Duaphine université, studying machine learning, data science and statistical modelling with a focus on biological problems.

BCPST Preparatory class, École Saint-Hilaire, Paris, France

2012-2014

2 year French preparatory class to prepare a nationally ranked exam for entry in the "Grande Écoles" ranked 201/1967 (Veto), ranked 481/2991 (Agro)

Languages

Mother tongue French & English Other languages¹

German² Mandarin Chinese³

Understanding				Speaking					Writing
	Listening		Reading		Interaction		Production		
B1	Independent	B1	Independent	В1	Independent	В1	Independent	B1	Independent
A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic

Common European Framework of Reference for Languages (CEFR)

Personal interests

Science, Technology, Playing Music, Drawing, Wine and Food, Hiking

Publications (Google scholar, ORCID)

Journal articles

- [1] Using Machine Learning and Big Data to Explore the Drug Resistance Landscape in HIV Luc Blassel, Anna Tostevin, Christian Julian Villabona-Arenas, Martine Peeters, Stéphane Hué, Olivier Gascuel PLOS Computational Biology 17.8 (Aug. 26, 2021), e1008873, Public Library of Science DOI: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008873
- [2] Drug Resistance Mutations in HIV: New Bioinformatics Approaches and Challenges Luc Blassel, Anna Zhukova, Christian J Villabona-Arenas, Katherine E Atkins, Stéphane Hué, Olivier Gascuel Current Opinion in Virology 51 (Dec. 1, 2021), pp. 56-64 DOI: 10.1016/j.coviro.2021.09.009
- [3] Origin, Evolution and Global Spread of SARS-CoV-2 Anna Zhukova, Luc Blassel, Frédéric Lemoine, Marie Morel, Jakub Voznica, Olivier Gascuel Comptes Rendus. Biologies 344.1 (2021), pp. 57-75 DOI: 10.5802/crbiol.29
- [4] Frédéric Lemoine, Luc Blassel, Jakub Voznica, Olivier Gascuel Bioinformatics (btaa871 Oct. 12, 2020) poi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa871

Accepted articles

Mapping-Friendly Sequence Reductions: Going beyond Homopolymer Compression Luc Blassel, Paul Medvedev, Rayan Chikhi to be published in iScience RECOMB-SEQ proceedings

Conference talks

[6] Mapping-Friendly Sequence Reductions: Going beyond Homopolymer Compression Luc Blassel, Paul Medvedev, Rayan Chikhi 2022

Paper to be presented at RECOM-SEQ 2022

² 1 month program at Goethe Institute in Schwäbisch Hall, Germany

 $^{^{}m 3}$ 5 month program at SISU Shanghai, Chian & 1 month program at UIR, Beijing, CN